the international agency for research on
cancer has published a report
classifying processed meat like bacon am
hot dogs lunch meat as a group one
carcinogen
how has that revelation been received by
governments in industry and just how
much cancer does processed meat cause
i'll answer those questions in this
two-part series
[Music]
it is perhaps rare in the history of
nations that one finds good reasons to
render homage to the generosity and
altruism of governments and those in
power but
the birth of the international agency
for research on cancer presents one of
those rare occasions
it all started
with a single letter from a bereaved
husband relating the suffering of his
wife after a cancer diagnosis cascading
into this open letter calling for
governments to devote half of one
percent of their military budgets to
fight
for life by attacking one of the
greatest plagues that weigh on humanity
and
18 months later the iarc was born in the
world health organization with what
overarching motive
cancer
prevention
the iarc is best known for its
monographs book-sized reports evaluating
whether or not some suspected carcinogen
does in fact cause cancer they're
generally accepted as close to a final
word as there is on whether or not
something is carcinogenic
and their 114th monograph published in
2018 was on meat after thoroughly
reviewing the accumulated scientific
literature a working group of 22 experts
from 10 countries after considering more
than 800 different studies concluded
their 500 page report by establishing
that something like a burger or pork
chop is probably carcinogenic probably
causes cancer
but processed meat was placed as a group
1 carcinogen which is the highest level
of certainty meaning that according to
the best available evidence the
consumption of processed meat causes
cancer
so that means foods like bacon cause
cancer ham hot dogs breakfast links
lunch meat cause cancer but their
definition also includes for example
turkey deli slices
specifically eating processed meat
causes colorectal cancer cancers of the
colon or rectum the second most deadly
cancer worldwide after lung cancer which
is caused largely from smoking
colorectal cancer is the second leading
cause of cancer death here in the united
states as well and it doesn't just
strike older people it's also leading
cause of cancer and death from cancer
earlier in life as well
the meat industry
wasn't happy calling it dramatic and
alarmist overreach
speaking of dramatic and alarmist
overreach one ag group in italy sent out
a press release just say no to terrorism
on meat
the gloves were off the meat industry in
canada tried to pressure the government
to cut off funds to the iarc asking the
health minister to pull all funding from
the agency after they dared to question
meat and the u.s meat industry did the
same thing
it's no surprise the iarc is under siege
by corporate interests trying to
challenge their cancer evaluations on
monsanto's roundup pesticide and meat
trying to discredit the agency and
undermine financial support
internal documents have revealed that
monsanto scientists for example casually
discussed ghost writing scientific
articles and suppressing any scientific
conflicts with the company's assertions
of safety
the chemical industry has joined the
corporate cacophony calling the iarc
monographs dubious and misleading
these are classic strategies straight
out of the tobacco industry playbook but
there's little to suggest that as a
corporate actor big tobacco differs
fundamentally from big boos or big food
for example
one recurring corporate talking point is
that basically the iarc never met a
carcinogen and didn't like
but the vast majority end up being
characterized as just possibly
carcinogenic or there really aren't
sufficient data to make a determination
either way and look they only spend time
looking at substances for which there's
already an existing body of scientific
literature indicating a degree of
carcinogenic hazard to humans so i mean
no wonder many of them end up indeed
carcinogenic
how did the iarc respond to all the
criticism
the world health organization received a
number of queries expressions of concern
and requests for clarification following
the publication of their meat and cancer
report they replied hey
we never told anyone to stop eating
processed meats look your body your
choice they just indicated that reducing
consumption of these products can reduce
the risk of a leading cancer killer so
hey you'll like cancer you do you
the iarc is just a research organization
that evaluates the evidence on the
causes of cancer after that what you do
with that information is up to you
the american cancer society was nice and
clear when it came to alcohol when it
comes to cancer it's best not to drink
but they got a little more wishy-washy
with processed meat suggesting people
can get away with just limiting their
intake the european commission was a
little clearer to reduce our risk of
cancer we should eat plenty of whole
grains pulses which are beans flippies
chickpeas lentils
vegetables and fruits limit sugary fatty
salty foods and straight up avoid soda
sausage and other processed meats after
all in answering the question how much
meat is safe to eat the iarc replied
that we don't yet know whether a safe
level exists period
[Music]
you